בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, א גוטע וואך *a gutteh voch*. Today's דף
*daf* is דף ל׳ *Daf Lamed*. We pick up where we're a
little bit behind, we pick up on the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* on
כ״ט עמוד ב׳ *Chaf Tes Amud Beis*, and we're in the middle
of the process of returning lost objects. And we just dealt with
the whole issue about what do you do if you find an
animal and you have to maintain it and support it, how to
deal with that. So now we're going to deal with other inanimate
objects but other things that have to be done in order to
keep them in good condition. Third, second line of wide line, משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah*. מצא ספרים sefarim *Matza sefarim*, if you find books, which
are really scrolls, קורא בהן לאחד לשלשים יום *Korei bahen l'echad lishloshim
yom*, you should read them once every thirty days in order to
air them out so they don't get moldy or moth eaten. ואם
אינו יודע לקרות *Ve'im
eino yodeiah likros*, and if you don't know how to read, you
know, גוללן *golelan*, so then just, you know, scroll, roll them up
from beginning to end, so open them up. You know, reading is
a convenient way as a, you know, maybe you also get a
side benefit of reading it,
but regardless even if you're not able to read it, just make
sure that you open it up and roll it from beginning to
end so you air it out. אבל לא ילמד בהם בתחלה *Aval
lo yilmad bahem batchilah*, don't learn something fresh in them that you
have never learned before because then you will maybe stay too much
on one place and the idea is to, you know, give scroll,
you know, expose a lot of it and also maybe you'll, you
know, you'll wear it down in one particular place. ולא יקרא אחר
עמו v'lo yikra acher imo. *Velo yikra acher imo*, don't read together
with another person because maybe you'll get in a bit of a
tugging war and it'll tear. מצא כסות מנערה אחד לשלשים יום *Matza
kesus mena'arah echad lishloshim yom*,
if you find some type of a garment, you should like, you
know, shake it out once every thirty days again, keep it from
getting, you know, moth eaten or whatever. Shake up the lice, shake
up the dust. ושוטחה לצרכה letzarcha, *Veshotechah l'tzarchah*, and you can spread
it out for its need, ולא לכבודו *velo lichvodo*, not for your
honor, meaning, you know, don't say, oh, I have some guests coming
over, what a perfect time to hang out that Armani suit that
I found, and you know, so then everyone, you know, it's a
way that people will think that you, exactly.
And we'll see about that in a minute because it's interesting by
the ספר sefer *sefer* you were able to get some side benefit.
Okay, but here you're not. כלי כסף וכלי נחושת klei kessef u-chlei
nechoshes משתמש בהן mishtamesh bahen לצרכן ולא לשחקן *Klei kesef u'klei nechoshet
mishtamesh bahen l'tzarchan velo l'shachkan*,
silver and copper vessels you can use them for
their to maintain them but not in a way that's going to
wear them out. Now of course let's say now when you're assuming
to maintain them, can you get a side benefit? Right? It doesn't
just say rinse them out or polish them. Presumably the use keeps
them in good shape, but don't like use them in a heavy
way, but it does sound like you can get some side benefit
in the process. כלי זהב וכלי זכוכית klei zahav ve-chlei zechuchis, לא
יגע בהן lo yiga bahen, *Klei zahav u'klei zechuchit lo yiga bahen*,
gold and glass vessels לא יגע בהן *lo yiga bahen*, don't use
them at all. Gold apparently as רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says, we're not
concerned that that would, you know, that doesn't need to be used,
won't oxidize, won't rust, and glass will more easily break. So one
it's not necessary and the other it's too dangerous. לא יגע בהן
*Lo yiga bahen* עד שיבוא אליהו *ad
sheyavo Eliyahu*, until אליהו *Eliyahu* comes. מצא שק או קופה וכל דבר
שאין דרכו ליטול *Matza sak o kupa vechol davar she'ein darko litol*,
if you found like a sack, a sackcloth or a box, and
anything that's not normally taken, הרי זה לא יטול *harei zeh lo
yitol*, don't take it. Now you might think what it might
mean find on the way, you don't take it home?
Well what you might think it means is like a sack or
a box might be something that's reasonably like the גמרא׳ס *Gemara's* discussion
before about ספק הינוח *safek hinuach*, something that might be intentionally left
there. But then it would not be described as אין דרכו ליטול
*ein darko litol*. It might be אין דרכו *ein darko*, you know,
to lose, you know, or was דרכו *darko* to be placed. So
the גמרא׳ס *Gemara's* going to understand that the issue here is not
that it's a ספק הינוח *safek hinuach* that it might have been
intentionally left there. The issue here is that it might be beneath
your dignity to return it. Now why דרכו *darko*, right? Well, דרכו
*darko* maybe, but I think דרכו *darko* means כדרך *kederech* of the
object, but כדרך *kederech* anyway, whatever it means, it means that it
would be beneath your dignity and this is going to be an
important principle of not having to return the objects if it's beneath
your dignity and we'll see about that. Yes, Charlie.
If back to the ספרים sefarim, *sefarim*, this implies ספרים sefarim, *sefarim*
on animal skins as we.
Yeah, presumably we're talking about parchment and presumably also we're not limiting
ourselves, although it's always an interesting question whether
ספר *sefer* means.
True, it's also a question whether ספרים sefarim *sefarim* means ספרי קודש
sifrei kodesh. *sifrei kodesh* or not or does it mean, you know,
any type of books because all their books were written in scrolls.
Okay, אמר שמואל *Amar Shmuel*, says שמואל *Shmuel*, המוצא תפילין Tefillin בשוק
שמין דמיהן ומניחן לאלתר *Hamotzei tefillin bashuk shamin demihen u'manichan l'alter*, if
you find תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* in the marketplace, you assess their value,
you put aside their money, you essentially purchase it for yourself or
maybe you could sell it to others, and then you if you
purchase it for yourself you can wear them right away.
Okay, so then why can't you just put them aside?
Well the גמרא׳ס *Gemara's* going to ask. מתיב רבבינא *Metiv Ravina*, מצא
ספרים sefarim, קורא בהן אחד לשלשים יום *Matza sefarim korei bahen echad
lishloshim yom*, if you find a ספר *sefer*, you read it once
every thirty days. ואם אינו יודע לקרות *Ve'im eino yodeiah likros*, and
if you don't know how to read. גוללן you, you scroll it.
גוללן אין, golan in, שמא מניחן לא. shamid minichan lo. So the
idea is, you do what you need to to maintain it, but
you're not allowed to just, you know, buy it. The buying it
was for things like animals or whatever that the maintenance was too
high. It's another way of asking, why are you what's special about
this that you're allowed to buy it right away? So אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, תפילין בר בי בר חבו Tefillin bar Bei bar Chavu
משכח שכיחי. mishkach shchichi.
תפילין Tefillin, you can buy as many תפילין Tefillin as you want
from this guy בר בי בר חבו. bar Bei bar Chavu. Go
onto Amazon, buy תפילין, Tefillin okay? There's all these ספרים sefarim stores
out there, ספרים, sefarim all these you know ספרי sifrei whatever תפילין
Tefillin, stores available. ספרים לא שכיחי, sefarim lo shchichi, but buying actual
scrolls, that's much harder to find, which is a fascinating you know
phenomenon to appreciate you know how rare you know was to have
a really whatever scrolls are, whether they're ספר תורה Sefer Torah scrolls
or just books, you know it was I mean I assume people
are aware about that. Before the printed book you know people that
had libraries of even like you know a few dozen scrolls it
was like a status, you know it was an enormous treasure, which
is why who was it that burnt down the Alexandrian library? Exactly.
Anyway, you know, which shows like this which was like this treasure
house of thousands of scrolls of the ancient world. It was like
a you know incalculable loss. Anyway, but apparently you know writing you
know we think that תפילין Tefillin, is a lot I mean it
is a lot of work. You got to make the boxes and
you got to make them exactly in the right way and you
got to make the straps and so on. But since like every
male Jew wore them, okay, there was a much bigger market and
there was a much they were much more plentiful. And therefore the
answer is, now this is interesting point though, right? Because it's still
not clear what's the pressure for you to sell. I mean it
it is sort of saying look if it's easily replaced and it
also sounds like you know nowadays people דווקא davka like I think
have a very personal attachment to their תפילין, Tefillin, you know? It's
my grandfather's תפילין, Tefillin I got a special I got דווקא davka
this this type of תפילין, Tefillin I checked the scrolls, I got
them from this type of סופר. sofer. This makes it sound like
there's very little personal attachment. It's an almost interchangeable type of an
object. So therefore what's the big deal? So you set aside the
money, you'll buy another one, okay? So it's not a big deal
as opposed to everything else which is either like the case you
know of animals like even animals more, it's like I want the
animal I broke in. You know or these things are harder to
replace. But even if all of that is true that תפילין Tefillin
are very easily replaced and there's not a high personal attachment, it's
not at all clear like what's the justification for doing it. Like
what's the big deal of putting תפילין Tefillin aside? So I really
don't know the answer the answer to that.
You have a pair of your own anyway, what do you need
another one for?
Right, but maybe it does mean that the fact that it says
מניחן manichan that you put them on, right? So maybe the point
is that if you need them, if you don't have your own
pair, you're entitled to do this because they are easily replaceable. Okay,
but if you do have your own pair then again it's hard
to understand what the need is, what the justification is.
And if they're so easily replaced it could also be that the
likelihood of finding סימנים simanim on them is...
that might be. So then right and that's an interesting point too.
Like you know having these תפילין tefillin locked up in a box
somewhere not doing anybody any good and they might be there for
an extremely long time. That's an interesting thought too, right. Because even
if it's not a high maintenance cost for you, it's still like
who's it helping that these תפילין Tefillin, are locked up in a
box somewhere waiting for their owner which might never show up? So
that's an interesting thought. So maybe they might as well let somebody
use them, I'll use the money in the interim if we פוסק
possek like רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, and right and everybody benefits and
if the owner shows up in five years from now he'll get
his money back. So that might be that might be that that
might be part of the part of the thinking. Yeah, Charlie?
Amazon does sell...
I'm sure they do.
Okay. Sixteen comments explaining they're not kosher.
I'm sure they're not. Moving on. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
תנו רבנן. Tnan rabbanan.
השואל ספר תורה מחבירו הרי זה לא ישאילנו לאחר. hasho'el Sefer Torah
mechaveiro harei zeh lo yash'ilenu l'acher. If you borrow a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, don't lend it to somebody else. פותחו וקורא בו. potcho
v'kore bo. Now you obviously open it and read from it of
course because that was the whole reason you borrowed it. ובלבד שלא
ילמד בו בתחילה, u-bilvad shelo yilmad bo betchila, but don't learn from
it at the out don't learn it from something you've never learned
before which is again by the way interesting because it makes it
clear that ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah were actually used to learn from
and not just in ritual purposes.
ולא יקרא אחר עמו. Don't have somebody read together with you, again
doesn't mean in שול shul just because you're learning the פרשה parsha
or whatever you're doing. Okay, וכן המפקיד ספר תורה אצל חבירו, ve-chen
hamaphkid Sefer Torah etzel chaveiro, and if you if you have if
you give it to somebody to watch for you, גוללו כל שנים
עשר חודש. golelo kol shneim asar chodesh. He should roll it every
twelve months, not every not every month, which is interesting. Why less?
Because you're reading the פרשה parsha on your own? Yeah, פותחו וקורא
בו, potcho v'kore bo, but you're not borrowing it now you're just
watching it to you're in my you're you're there to just protect
it for me. Okay
פותחו וקורא בו potcho v'kore bo and you can open it and
read from it. אם בשבילו פותחו, im bishvilo potcho, but if you're
doing it just because you want to use it, not to... But
if you're doing it just because you want to use it, not
to, you know, not fundamentally to air it out, אסור, assur, it's
forbidden. סומכוס אומר, Sumchus omer, בחדש, bechodesh, בחדש, excuse me, בחדש שלושים
יום, if it's a new ספר תורה, sefer torah, then you should
use, then you should open it up every thirty days if you're
watching it for me. בישן, beyashan,
and if it's an old one, שנים עשר חודש, shneim asar chodesh,
twelve months, because presumably a new one and an old one maybe
has a greater chance of tearing.
Let's see if that's what רש"י Rashi says.
It says
because it's going to get moldier quicker.
The older one would get moldy quicker?
No, the newer one.
Why would a newer one get moldier quicker?
Because the older ones are already moldy.
I don't know.
I don't know. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, אחד זה ואחד זה,
שנים עשר חודש, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer echad zeh v'echad zeh
shneim asar chodesh. either way twelve months. Okay, now let's unpack this
whole thing. אמר מר, Amar mar, השואל ספר תורה מחבירו הרי זה
לא ישאילנו לאחר. hashoel sefer torah mechaveiro harei zeh lo yashilenu le'acher.
Don't lend it to somebody else.
By the way, notice on the one hand this says ספר תורה
sefer torah as opposed to the משנה Mishnah, which says ספרים, sefarim
which could be an argument that our משנה Mishnah is talking about
just general books and again maybe not even ספרי קודש. On the
other hand, since all the rules are the exact same as the
משנה, Mishnah, you could basically infer from this that our משנה mishna,
does mean ספר תורה, sefer torah, right? Because it's all the exact
same parameters. Don't read two people, don't read the same with a
new topic, and so on. Okay, anyway, let's take a look. אמר
מר, Amar mar, השואל ספר תורה מחבירו לא ישאילנו לאחר. hashoel sefer
torah mechaveiro lo yashilenu le'acher. מאי איריא ספר תורה? mai irya sefer
torah? Why specifically don't lend a ספר תורה sefer torah to somebody
if you borrowed it? אפילו כל מילי נמי, afilu kol milei nami,
don't, anything you borrow, you're not entitled to lend it to someone
else. דאמר ריש לקיש, De'amar Reish Lakish, כאן שנה רבי, kan shanah
Rebbe, here Rebbe taught, not here, but in another גמרא, Gemara, based
on the משנה, mishna אין השואל רשאי להשאיל, ein hashoel rashai lehashil,
a borrower cannot lend out the object he borrowed, ואין השוכר רשאי
להשכיר, ve'ein hasocher rashai lehashkir, or somebody who rented an object cannot
rent it out. Okay, so it's a general rule. So why do
you have to tell it by ספר תורה? sefer torah? No, ספר
תורה איצטריכא ליה. sefer torah itztricha lei. No, it's a חידוש chiddush
by a ספר תורה. sefer torah. You might have thought a ספר
תורה sefer torah is an exception to the rule. מהו דתימא, mahu
deteima, I might have thought ניחא ליה לאיניש דתיעבד מצוה בממוניה, nicha
lei le'inish detei'aved mitzvah bemamonei, a person wants to do a מצוה
mitzvah with their money. A person is happy if I lend Michael
my ספר תורה, sefer torah, I'm really happy for anybody to use
my ספר תורה, sefer torah, let somebody else, let more people learn
תורה. Torah. So implicitly I'm okay, maybe you would argue I'm okay
with him lending it out to other people. קא משמע לן, ka
mashma lan, not that way. That if there's a fear that it
might get damaged or whatever, we don't say that. I think I've
mentioned before, you know, like this comes up commonly that if you
come to שול shul and, you know, you have some, you need
to put on תפילין or a טלית tallit and somebody left theirs,
you can generally assume that they'd be okay with you putting it
on briefly and also because there's not a high concern that you'll
come to damage those things. But we generally do not say that
in the case of, by books, okay? Because people, A, books people
sort of take and never return. I have plenty of books that
have never been returned. Okay, and number two, you know, and number
two, you know, books are more easily damaged. You spill coffee on
them, you tear them, and so on. That's why some people have
the practice to write inside their book like מותר להשתמש במקומו, mutar
lehishtamesh bimkomo, like you can use it if you keep it right
here. Like you can, you know, if you need to use it,
you know, don't take it back to your place, you know, but
while you're here you can use it, okay? Or things like that.
But anyway, but this is a, this actually is a general הלכה.
halacha. On the one hand we do say there's an implicit assumption
you would want somebody to do a מצוה mitzvah with your object.
On the other hand, limited
by cases where you'd be concerned that your object might get lost
or damaged in the process. Yes.
Wouldn't that be similar to the apple we were talking about, you
need permission before taking?
So yes, but that's what we're saying. There are some cases where
you can assume that there's like permission is automatically given from the
outset. Okay. And so like things like, again, that it's allowed for
people to do a מצוה mitzvah with my object
and there's really a very tiny chance that any damage will occur,
there the גמרא Gemara says we are entitled to assume that people
are implicitly okay with it from the get-go. Okay, but yes, that
gets back to the יאוש שלא מדעת. yei'ush shelo mada'at. What does
that mean from the get-go? Did anybody stop and think that at
any time? You know, how does that fit into the whole יאוש
שלא מדעת yei'ush shelo mada'at concept is a good, is an important
question.
So you're saying you don't have automatic permission, is that what you're
saying?
So normally you do not have automatic permission. Now the גמרא Gemara
again was talking about parchment scrolls which were extremely expensive. Right, I
understand. The general assumption is, you know, that the same is true
even about normal book types of ספרים because again they are often
not returned or easily damaged. I mean not super easily damaged, but
you know things do rip, they fall, it hurts the binding, people
spill coffee on them or so on. If you know somebody's totally
cool with people using their ספרים, then that's different.
So is that the reason why somebody would have to write in
the book permission?
Oh, because we generally assume, because no, we generally assume by ספרים
that you generally don't have permission because you don't.
Right, so why would you need to write in the book only
use it here?
Because that's giving permission to at least use here. If you don't
write it in the book, you can't even use it even standing
right there. Right. Okay.
All right.
Libraries also do this, ספרים in a שול. shul.
Right, but ספרים in a שול shul are there to be used.
Now what David is saying might be true, could be that for
most people... If you use it without taking it to your place
and without having a cup of coffee in your hand, right, you
know, maybe maybe we could assume that most people would be okay
with you doing that, but it does raise that interesting question. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, let's keep on going.
וכן vechen
okay ובלבד שלא ילמד בו בתחילה u'vilvad shelo yilmad bo batchila sorry
I skipped a line
פותח וקורא בו פשיטא poteach v'korei bo pshita so you can open
it and read from it. Obviously. דלמאי שרי d'lamai sharei this is
not a question of an אבידה aveida or פקדון. pikadon. This is
something you borrowed. Of course you can open it and read from
it. Why else did you borrow it? What to look at it?
So no. ומאי שרי מיניה u'mai sharei minei נו ספר איצטריכא ליה.
no sefer itztricha lei. No, yes, that is obvious, but that's a
lead in to the end. Okay ובלבד שלא ילמד בו בתחילה u'vilvad
shelo yilmad bo batchila but what you're not allowed to do is
learn something you've never learned from it. Even if I lent you
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah it's understood to be like, you know,
a type of a, of a certain type of a use but
not an intensive use. וכן המפקיד ספר תורה אצל חבירו גוללו כל
שנים עשר חודש. vechen hamaphkid sefer torah etzel chaveiro gollo kol shneim
asar chodesh. If you entrust it the person has to scroll it
every twelve months. חדש פותחו וקורא בו chadash potcho v'korei bo sorry
did I skip a line? גוללו כל שנים עשר חודש. gollo kol
shneim asar chodesh. No, I'm sorry, no. גוללו כל שנים עשר חודש
פותחו וקורא בו מה עבידתיה. gollo kol shneim asar chodesh potcho v'korei
bo mah avidatei. So in that case it says you scroll it
every twelve months and open it and read it. So what are
you doing opening and reading it? If it's a פקדון pikadon so
you should be scrolling it in order to air it out. But
then why are you but then by asking afterwards, after saying that
you have to scroll it every twelve months it says you read
it, sounds like we're letting you read it just for your own
needs. Why are you allowed to read it for your own needs?
It's a פקדון. pikadon. You're already scrolling it every twelve months. So
ותו אם בשבילו פותחו אסור. v'tu im bishvilo potcho assur. If you're
opening it up for your sake, it's forbidden. הא אמרת פותח וקורא
בו. ha amart poteach v'korei bo. You said you're allowed to open
it and read from it again, which sounds like for your own
needs, right? If you already told me for the ספר's needs scroll
it every twelve months, then open it, then saying you can open
it sounds like for your own needs. But that doesn't make sense
and you explicitly say you're not allowed to open it for your
own needs. So what's the story? So the גמרא Gemara says no
הכי קאמר hachi ka amar אם כשהוא גוללו פותח וקורא בו מותר.
im keshehu gollo poteach v'korei bo mutar. If you want to incidentally
use it as you are fundamentally taking care of it, as you
are scrolling it and wrapping it and you're taking care and your
basic reason that you're dealing with it now is to air it
out, and along the way you're allowed to, you know, read from
it, okay?
So that's okay, okay if it's in part of the process of
taking care of it and scrolling it. אם בשבילו פתחו im bishvilo
patcho
but if you fundamentally are opening it because you say oh you
know like, you know you're having an argument about a פסוק pasuk
or something you want to check up a פסוק. pasuk. Oh well
I got this ספר תורה Sefer Torah that's being kept by me,
let's open it up and look at it. If the basic reason
you're opening it up is for your interest that's forbidden. Okay? But
if you're doing it to take care of the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah then along the way you're allowed to read from it. סומכוס
אומר בחדש שלושים יום בישן שנים עשר חודש. Sumchos omer bechadash shloshim
yom be'yashan shneim asar chodesh. New ones every thirty days, old ones
twelve months. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov omer,
אחד זה ואחד זה echad zeh ve'echad zeh, שנים עשר חודש. shneim
asar chodesh, Regardless twelve months. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב היינו תנא קמא.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hainu tanna kamma. Isn't that the תנא קמא?
tanna kamma? תנא קמא Tanna kamma said twelve months and he's just
repeating twelve months. So you could say it is, he's just pushing
back on סומכוס, Sumchos, but the גמרא Gemara wants to have him
be a different opinion. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב אומר אחד זה ואחד זה שלושים יום. ela eima
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer echad zeh v'echad zeh shloshim yom. No,
he would say regardless of new or old thirty days, and that
also makes it convenient because now we're able to say that that's
the author of our משנה, mishna. because our משנה mishna said thirty
days. And until now we haven't had an opinion that said thirty
days both for old and new, right? The תנא קמא tanna kamma
said twelve months, סומכוס Sumchos said thirty days for new, for which
one did he say it for? For old. So now we have
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov saying thirty days for
either. And that way we're able to then assume is the author
of our משנה. Mishnah: אבל לא ילמד בו בתחילה ולא יקרא אחר
עמו. aval lo yilmad bo batchila v'lo yikra acher imo. Don't learn
from it at the outset and don't have somebody read it with
you. This is going back to our משנה Mishnah on אבידה aveida
that you found. ורמינהו. v'reminhu. I'll ask you on this. לא יקרא
פרשה וישנה ולא יקרא בו פרשה ויתרגם. lo yikra parsha v'yishneh v'lo
yikra bo parsha v'yitargem. So again there's a ברייתא braita presumably about
the case of finding an אבידה. aveida.
Don't read a פרשה parsha and read it twice, and which is
similar to בתחילה. batchila. Even if you're familiar with it, if you
stay in one location again you might be a little too vigorous
use of that you know of that space and it might rub
it out or something.
And don't read the פרשה parsha and then translate it. It's also
staying too much in one place and it's fundamentally more serving your
needs than just keeping the scroll moving and keeping it for you
know being scrolling for its needs.
שניים מקרא ואחד תרגום? shnayim mikra v'echad targum?
Yeah, so that's a good point, I mean good for noticing that.
The reason you would read it twice and the reason you would
translate it might be specifically to do שניים מקרא ואחד תרגום. shnayim
mikra v'echad targum. Right.
That's how ancient that is.
Right. Well yeah, correct, absolutely. ולא יפתח בו יותר מג' דפין. v'lo
yiftach bo yoter mi'gimmel dapin.
And do not when you're opening it up and scrolling it open
up more than
three parchment, not columns, you know, but three parchment, sometimes you have
like four columns on a parchment, right? I mean that's a large
amount of space depending on how many columns. forms you have per
parchment, per piece of parchment,
because again, that would just more easily tear.
Where am I?
I lost my place.
Okay. וגם בלא יקראו בו שלושה בני אדם בכרך אחד V'gam b'lo
yikre'u bo shlosha b'nei adam b'chrach echad and three people should not
read it at the same time. Anyway, all of that is more
restrictions but the question is it says don't have three people read
it at the same time, and our Mishnah says two people. השנים
קוראים, Ha-shnayim korim, it sounds like two people could read. אמר אביי
לא קשיא כאן בענין אחד כאן בשני עניינים. Amar Abaye lo kashya
kan b'inyan echad kan b'shnei inyanim. The question is are they reading
in the same location or in different locations. Now which is better?
So Rashi says that if they're reading different parts, it is, it's
better. Like I'm going to read over here, and I'm reading נצבים,
Nitzavim, and you're reading over here, and you're reading, you know, I'm,
you know,
I'm reading here נצבים Nitzavim and you're reading over here and you're
reading וילך. Vayeilech. Okay, so we're not going to get into a
tugging war, okay, which is funny because you might say like no,
like I got to get to the next piece or I got
anyway, you might think that if they're in different locations they are
sort of pulling it in different directions. But anyway, Rashi says no,
I'm focused on my part, you're focused on your part. Whereas if
you're all reading in the same place, it's like we're all competing
for the same, you know, to look at the same piece so
it might get into more of a tugging war and there even
two is a problem. Okay, now the Gemara continues.
Okay. מנער כסותו מן האורח לשלושים יום. Menayer kesuso min ha-orech l'shloshim
yom. So if you find some garment you shake it out every
30 days. למימרא דניחא ליה, L'meimra d'nicha lei, that sounds like shaking
it out is good for it. ואמר רבי יוחנן מי שיש לו
גרדי אומן בתוך ביתו, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan mi she-yesh lo gardi uman
b'toch beito,
so you know Rabbi Yochanan says in a little bit of a
sarcastic way, if you have an expert tailor in your house, then
ינכסנו בכל יום, yenachasenu b'chol yom, then you should go ahead and
shake out your garment every single day, which is his way of
saying that shaking out your garment too much is not good for
your garment, it's going to cause it to tear. Okay, I don't
know if you've ever seen this, whenever I take my clothes to
the dry cleaners, they got a little sign up that says like,
you know, keep your clothes in good shape, you know like whatever
like you know dry clean them regularly. Of course the point is
no, actually, if you dry clean them regularly it's bad for them,
you shouldn't overly dry clean your, you know, your garment. So that's
what he's saying. If you want, you know, if you've got a
tailor on-premises, גזונטהייט, gesundheit,
go ahead and shake out your clothes every day. Okay, but it's
really not good to over, to do it too much. So the
Gemara says אמרי, Amri, which is the Gemara's answer. פשיטא, Pshita, בכל
יום קשי ליה אחת לשלושים יום מעלי ליה, b'chol yom kashi lei
achat l'shloshim yom ma'aly lei, every day is bad for it,
but once a month that's actually keeping it in good condition. Okay.
איבעית אימא לא קשיא הא בחד והא בתרי. Iba'is eima lo kashya
ha b'chad v'ha b'trei.
Is one person shaking it out or two people shaking it out?
One person shaking it out is not as vigorous, so that'll be
a more, that you know that's a way to do, that'll be
good for it. Two people shaking it out could be a little
bit too vigorous. It might get it cleaner but it might not
be good for the, you know, for the durability of the garment.
איבעית אימא לא קשיא הא בידא והא בחוטרא. Iba'is eima lo kashya
ha b'yada v'ha b'chutra. Are you shaking it out with your hand,
which again is not so vigorous, so it's not super clean that
way but it keeps it in good shape? Or are you banging
it with a stick, you know, you see people sometimes beat rugs
or something, right, which gets it much more clean but obviously, you
know, you know, is not good for its longevity.
This is not talking about washing in the river and beating it
against a rock.
Right,
no, this does not, this is shaking it out for the dust.
Yeah, that's what it seems to be. Which does raise an interesting
question about should you be, you know, should you be cleaning it
but like why, like if it wasn't dirty and whatever, why should
you be, like if your stuff hangs in your closet, right, you
don't clean it if it's going to hang there for 12 months,
you might want to get the dust out of it but it
doesn't need to be laundered.
I want to know how many pieces of clothing a person has
and how many pieces of clothing a person has.
I understand, but this maintenance is, it's not getting dirty, it doesn't
need to be laundered, right, so that's not the maintenance that it
requires. Okay. איבעית אימא לא קשיא הא בדמרא והא דכיתנא. Iba'is eima
lo kashya ha b'damra v'ha d'chitna.
Is it made out of wool or is it made out of
flax? Wool is more, now Rashi says I think wool is less
durable, קשי ליה, kashi lei, Rashi says, שנמתחת ונקראת, she-nimtechet v'nikre'et,
that wool will stretch more and tear. But I would think that
wool is a more durable garment fabric than flax. Anyway, than linen.
Anyway, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, since we had Rabbi Yochanan
saying these like good practical advice about taking care of your garments,
we're going to have a series of statements along the same, in
the same vein. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan said Rabbi Yochanan,
כסא דחרשין ולא כסא דפושרין. kasa d'charshin v'lo kasa d'poshrin.
I'd rather have a cup filled with, you know, of witchcraft that
you know that witches had done some witchcraft over, rather than a
cup of lukewarm water which is bad for your health. ולא אמרן
אלא בכלי מתכות, V'lo amran ela b'chlei machteches, but that's only lukewarm
water in a metal type of a vessel, אבל בכלי חרס לית
לן בה, aval b'chlei cheres leit lan bah,
but in a pottery it's not a problem. I don't know, maybe
they were concerned about like lead poisoning or some type of
things or anyway. ובכלי מתכות נמי U'v'chlei machteches nami which also could
get rid of various types of impurities or whatever. ולא אמרן אלא
דלא שדי ביה ציבא Velo amran ela delo shadi bei tzeva and
even when and even when it is a problem and it's lukewarm
and it's not boiling, of course when when's it why had to
say boiling? Just what might mean brought to boil? I know. It
could be. Rashi says רותח Roteach which means currently boiling, but yes,
it could mean have been boiled which would make more sense. And
that's a way to get out the impurities. Anyway, even then it's
not a problem
if it hasn't had like had something had something thrown into it,
something to Rashi says some herbs or something like
that. אבל שדי ביה ציבא Aval shadi bei tzeva if it had
something added to it לית לן בה Leit lan bah it's not
a problem. Fine. That's a health issue. ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi
Yochanan, מי שהניח, Mi shehiniach, back to sort of protecting your possessions.
מי שהניח לו אביו מעות הרבה Mi shehiniach lo aviv ma'ot harbeh
ורוצה לאבדן, Verotze le'abdan, if your father left you a lot of
money and you want to lose them, so run for president.
No. ילבש בגדי פשתן, Yilbash bigdei pishtan, wear flax garments, וישתמש בכלי
זכוכית, Veyishtamesh bichlei zuchuchit, and use glass vessels, וישכור פועלים ואל ישב
עמהם, Veyiskor po'alim ve'al yeshev imahem, and hire a lot of workers
and don't supervise them. This would be a good way to waste
your money. Okay, to get rid of all that extra money you've
got.
So the Gemara now looks at this. ילבש בגדי פשתן, Yilbash bigdei
pishtan, when we say wearing flax linen garments, cause those are more
easily get ruined. בכתנא דרומיתא, Bechitna deromita, so that's talking about a
certain type of a linen. I don't know if that means Roman,
is that how they translate it? Roman linen? They said Roman linen?
Okay, Roman linen. וישתמש בכלי זכוכית, Veyishtamesh bichlei zuchuchit, glass vessels, בזוגיתא
חיוורתא, Bezuchita chivarta, white glass, maybe that means totally clear glass, which
is extremely expensive. וישכור פועלים ואל ישב עמהם, Veyiskor po'alim ve'al yeshev
imahem, hire workers and don't supervise them, תרגומא, Targuma, we explained that
this means בתורי Betorei specifically by oxen or Tosfos says by ox
drivers, people that handle the oxen,
דנפיש הפסדייהו, Denafish hefsidaihu, that back those cause a great deal of
loss if they're not properly supervised. Okay, moving on. שוטחה לצרכה ולא
לכבודה, Shotecha letzorcha velo lichvoda, back to now taking care of the
garment, you can spread it out for its purposes but not to
bring honor to yourself. Let's say it's a nice rug or something,
I've got some company coming, I'll spread it out, it'll make me
look like I've got this nice garment and so on. Yes.
General question. How long am I doing this? Until when? What's the
time frame until when let's say...
Yeah, that's a good question. So when can
you assume יאוש Ye'ush after a certain passage of time? The general
assumption is no, meaning there was a Gemara before that spoke about
twelve months that Rashi read to mean that you assume יאוש Ye'ush
but Tosfos pushed back on that. The general assumption is you don't
assume after a long period of time just cause it's taken a
long time that there's יאוש, Ye'ush, but although maybe there are some
cases that it is reasonable. Anyway, it doesn't matter, even if there's
יאוש Ye'ush once you picked it up, you're חייב Chayav to return
it even if יאוש Ye'ush occurs afterwards, right? That's an important other
principle. יאוש Ye'ush only allows you to keep it if you encountered
it after יאוש. Ye'ush. But if you encountered it before יאוש Ye'ush
you're obligated to return. But the other question is like is there
a time I could just sell it and put the money away,
so I don't have to do this regular maintenance, right? And it's
never said by these inanimate objects. And the implication is that if
something actually costs you like out-of-pocket expenses, like paying for animal upkeep
and buying their food, that's when I can sell it and just
put away the money. This type of thing which is an effort,
it's like just my effort beating it out, but it's not an
actual expense. It's an expense of time, but not of money. It
sounds like it's ongoing, right?
You still beating this thing out once every- I know.
It sounds like a halakhic nightmare anyway.
I know. So it is interesting. It gets to that similar question
about the תפילין, right, where which was inanimate and you were allowed
to sell it. Are there some types of ways in which this
would begin to parallel the animal scenario?
So that's a good question. Have we seen that, that if the
owner is מיאש Meyayesh after I've picked it up, I'm still obligated
to- Well, you're right, we- I know,
we have not, I think it's been implicit very long, we have
not made it that explicit. I mean it sort of came up
with the whole מחלוקת Machlokes of אביי ורבא Abaye veRava of יאוש
שלא מדעת, Ye'ush shelo mida'at, right? Because that all assumed that if
יאוש שלא מדעת לא הוי יאוש, Ye'ush shelo mida'at lo havei ye'ush,
then when you pick it up you remain obligated to return it
even if the יאוש Ye'ush occurs later. How- Right, so you're right,
but you're right, I don't think we've said it as explicitly as
it needed to be said, which is- that's the principle. Right. I
mean, look, it's implicit in the Gemara before when Rava says if
you find an אבידה Aveidah and you hover around it waiting for
the owner to be מיאש Meyayesh and then you take it, then
you're עובר Over on לא תוכל להתעלם, Lo tuchal lehis'alem, which makes
it the only reason you'd be hovering... around it is because once
you picked it up, יאוש yi'ush afterwards wouldn't do you any good.
Okay? But yes, but that's an important principle. Now, the reason that
that might be true is, now once we're talking about it I'll
say one other sentence about this, you could conceptualize in one of
two ways. You could say, well, once you picked it up before
יאוש yi'ush you have a מצוה mitzvah of השב תשיבם hasheiv tishiveim
and that מצוה mitzvah remains even after the יאוש yi'ush comes about.
So, yes, there is יאוש yi'ush and you know, who knows, maybe
some third person, you know, took it from me or if I
lost it, I mean, whatever, we could start imagining whether a third
person, let's say I lost the אבידה aveidah I was supposed to
be watching and after the owner is מיאש, me'ayaish, right, and some
third person found it, would maybe he would own it, but it
doesn't matter, my relationship to it is already defined as השב תשיבם
hasheiv tishiveim as a מצוה mitzvah and that doesn't change after יאוש.
yi'ush. The other way of explaining it is once I picked it
up I become a שומר shomer as we discussed before. And am
I a שומר חנם shomer chinam or am I a שומר שכר,
shomer sachar, but I am now protecting it on behalf of the
owner. So if I'm protecting it on behalf of the owner, his
יאוש yi'ush might be meaningless because he's מיאש me'ayaish on something that's
being watched for him. So we discussed earlier, can I be מיאש
me'ayaish on something that I lost on my property? Well, if I'm
מיאש me'ayaish on it after you found it, essentially I'm מיאש me'ayaish
on something that's on my property because you're watching it for me.
Okay, so anyway, that is interesting and we haven't sort of said
that as explicitly as it needed to be said, so it's good
to say it now. Okay, moving on, the גמרא Gemara says like
this: שוטחה לצרכה ולא לכבודה, shotecha l'tzarchah v'lo lichvodah, you can spread
it out for its needs but not to bring honor for yourself.
Although we did see before by the ספר תורה Sefer Torah that
you can incidentally read it as you're scrolling it up. So איבעיא
להו, ibaia lehu, they raise the question: לצרכה ולצרכו מאי? l'tzarchah ul'tzarcho
mai? Let's say you're going to do it, you're going to spread
it out both for your needs and for its needs. What's the
story? Now תוספות Tosafot says this is not a formalist question like,
oh, it's always אסור assur to get some incidental benefit, because we
saw before by the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you can read
from it as you're scrolling it.
So תוספות Tosafot says this is really a more practical issue that
if you're also serving, if partly the reason you're doing it is
to serve your needs, then we should not allow that in cases
where it might lead to overuse. So some type of a thing
about spreading out a rug or whatever it might be, you might
leave it out too long if you want the guests to appreciate
it and you want them to see you have a nice rug.
Whereas if you're reading a תורה Torah and you go by the
restrictions we gave you—don't have two people read it, don't read it
two times, you know, don't read it something you've never read before—then
there's no concern that your incidental use might come to damage it.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot wants to understand it's not an absolute rule
that whether you can, that you can't get incidental benefit. But maybe
should we allow incidental benefit in cases where there's might a possible
concern that it might bring about some damage or misuse to the
object? That's the way תוספות Tosafot frames the question. You start to
rationalize, you know. Right, exactly. Exactly. And that's, by the way, that's
another important difference which I wanted to say, which תוספות Tosafot doesn't
I think spell out clearly, that part of the question might not
just be what is the likelihood that it might get misused, but
the difference between what's my fundamental engagement with the object? Like by
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah it's like as you can, as you're
scrolling it for taking care of it, you can read from it
along the way. Okay, that's different than saying, oh, let's, let's take
out the ספר תורה Sefer Torah because, A, I need to scroll
it and, B, I need to read from it. Right? When your
initial motivation is your own use, right, then that might be a
greater level of concern. So that might be also part of the
issue here. Not the question of can I incidentally use it while
I'm taking care of it, but can I initially, you know, you
know, spread it out if my initial motivation is also informed by
my own needs? Yes, but the point you're making is that it's
hard to, once you get into that it's hard to tell which
one it is. Right, right. How can we ever know how pure
our motivations are? For your own self, like you get, you get,
you rationalize that it might be good to take care... Right, exactly.
Exactly. Exactly. So תוספות Tosafot talks like this, the very last line,
he sees it conceptualized as a שומר, shomer, right? He's a שומר.
shomer. יש לעיין, yeish l'ayein, almost sounds like you've got the obligation.
You do have the obligation. Right. יש לעיין. yeish l'ayein. Yes. To...
yes. Okay, so if you're doing it for its needs and your
needs, what's the story? תא שמע: ta shema: שוטחה לצרכה, shotecha l'tzarchah,
which is, not שחטה shachta but שוטחה, shotecha, נכונה, nechona, שוטחה לצרכה,
shotecha l'tzarchah, so you can spread it out for its needs. לצרכה
אין, l'tzarchah in, only for its needs. הא לצרכה ולצרכו לא, ha
l'tzarchah ul'tzarcho lo, if it's both your needs and its needs, no,
you can't. That's implicit because it says for its needs. אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, but let's look at the end of the משנה: Mishna
אבל לא לכבודה, aval lo lichvodah, you're not allowed to do it
for to bring honor for yourself. So that sounds like if it's
exclusively for your needs it's a problem. לכבודה דלא, lichvodah d'lo, הא
לצרכה ולצרכו שפיר דמי, ha l'tzarchah ul'tzarcho shapir dami, if it's both
for its needs and your needs, that would be good. אלא מהא
ליכא למשמע מינה, ela meha lika l'mishma mina, once again the גמרא
Gemara says you cannot infer because the משנה Mishna often gives the
two extremes and does not talk about the middle cases. Right, that's
the classic, you know, Aristotle's point about the excluded middle. Right, so
Aristotle says, you know, the excluded middle is the difference between of...
know the opposite or whatever of ice cream of chocolate is not
vanilla it's like not chocolate because if you say I like chocolate
and I don't like vanilla then you haven't told the this whole
big range of excluded middle right so the best clearest way to
define things is A and not A, not A versus B, A
versus B leads to an excluded middle so the משנה mishna, often
has the excluded middle and the גמרא Gemara says you therefore don't
know from the משנה mishna what the story is with the excluded
middle. Did this conversation so bore you? Never mind. Alright, I thought
you were going to tell me you like Greek yogurt instead of
ice cream. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this תא שמע,
ta shma, so there תא שמע ta shma says the גמרא, Gemara,
we can just learn Greek wisdom. Okay, אלא מהא ליכא למשמע ela
meha leka lemishma תא שמע ta shma לא ישטחנה לא על גבי
מיטה ולא על גבי מגוד lo yishtachena lo al gabi mita velo
al gabi magod לצרכו letzarcho for your needs like so that everybody
could would come in and see oh look at this beautiful rug
this guy's got that's airing it out. אבל ישטחנה על גבי מיטה
ועל גבי מגוד לצרכה aval yishtachena al gabi mita veal gabi magod
letzarcha but you can do it for its needs, again telling us
the two extremes without the middle. נזדמנו לו אורחין, nizdamnu lo orchin,
now let's say you happen to have guests dropping by, לא ישטחנה
lo yishtachena לא על גבי מיטה lo al gabi mita ולא על
גבי מגוד velo al gabi magod בין לצרכו בין לצרכה bein letzarcho
bein letzarcha whether for its or your needs, which is exactly the
point about the rationalization. If you have guests dropping by, don't even
do it, even if you think in your mind you're doing it
just to take care of it, because when there are guests dropping
by clearly there's something else going on about why you're doing it.
But that would be a case that you believe you're totally doing
it לצרכה, letzarcha so worst case scenario it's לצרכה letzarcha and לצרכו,
letzarcho, and we still say don't do it. So that seems to
be pretty good evidence. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם
דמיקלא קלי לה, shani hatam demikla kali lah, by doing it when
guests are coming by you're effectively burning it. How are you burning
it? You're destroying it. How is that true? אי משום עינא ei
mishum eina because either they'll give it the עין הרע, ayin hara,
they'll say whoa look at that fancy rug that guy's got, and
they'll give it the עין הרע ayin hara okay and then that'll
cause it to have some damage to to occur. אי משום גנבי
ei mishum ganvei or from a more less metaphysical perspective you're encouraging
people to now come steal it. Everyone will say wow did you
see ראובן Reuven had that Persian rug must be worth thousands of
dollars okay and that's going to lead to it getting doubled. So
it has nothing to do with the fact that you will wear
it too thin or something of that nature but that it is
actually dangerous in this circumstance to be doing it. Yes, also people
are just less responsible when there's guests around like if your house
is full of people over because it just increases the chances. Right
right, but that would be but that would be relevant to the
general issue of לצרכו ולצרכה letzarcho uletzarcha that once it's לצרכו letzarcho
you're being even though you're just saying it's it's even more dangerous
than normal לצרכו letzarcho because guests are around and they'll they'll spill
their drinks on it or whatever. Right, this is a גמרא בבלי,
Gemara Bavli, right? Yeah, it wouldn't be a Persian rug, it'd just
be a rug. Okay, that's a good point. תא שמע, ta shma,
come and hear. Okay, הכניסה לרבקה hichnisa lerivka או לדושה, o ledasha,
so this is a question whether this is talking about a פרה
אדומה para aduma about an עגלה ערופה. egla arufa. רש"י Rashi there
says about an עגלה ערופה. egla arufa. Either way, it's an animal
that's not allowed to do work, right? עגלה, egla, a calf that
you're going to use for עגלה ערופה egla arufa is אשר לא
עובד בה, asher lo ubad bah, that it was not worked. No,
is that עובד בה ubad bah is maybe that's talking about the
actual the הנחל. hanachal. But anyway, but either way the עגלה ערופה
egla arufa and the and the פרה אדומה para aduma you're not
allowed to do any work. So let's say you put it into
a barn and while it was in there it threshed. Now רש"י
Rashi actually says a רבקה, rivka, I don't know how they translate
there in the English, רש"י Rashi says it means like some type
of a harness but that doesn't really work with the rest of
the of the discussion. I always understood it was a barn. How
do they translate it? It translates it as yoke, which makes a
barn a harness. That's how רש"י Rashi translates it. It doesn't exactly
sit for well let's keep on let's read it that way anyway.
So well, a yoke is different, a yoke is a
yoke, a yoke actually makes
it פסול, pasul, no but
harness is just to to
bind it to the other animals it's not certainly not a yoke,
it might be a harness. Anyway, so let's say you just you
know connected it to these other animals and you just for whatever
reason you just didn't want it to go running off or something
and while it was with them it threshed the grain because the
reason you sometimes use harness animals together is that they should all
be threshing grain. כשרה, kshera, that's incidental, you did not intentionally have
it do work and it doesn't invalidate it. It's not an animal
that has been has been worked which cannot be used for a
פרה אדומה para aduma or עגלה ערופה egla arufa depending on which
one we're talking about. בשביל שתינק ותדוש, bishvil shetinak vetadush, let's say
you harnessed it together so that it should nurse from its mother,
which is why I don't understand how you how it's able to
nurse when it's being harnessed that sort of limits its mobility. But
anyway and but you want it not only to nurse you also
want it to thresh while it's there, in that case פסולה psula
it's invalid.
So there you wanted it to do two things, something which was
לצרכה
right for it to nurse and לצרכו letzarcho to serve your interest
while it's
nursing it'll also be trampling on the grain and that invalidates. So
the גמרא Gemara says הכא לצרכו
ולצרכה הוא וקתני פסולה,
hacha
letzarcho
uletzarcha hu ukatani psula, that invalidates it.
Of course, according to תוספות Tosafot it's completely irrelevant like that's a
formal question of was it considered to be worked whereas here it's
a question about is it you know It is sufficient taking care
of the object, right?
They're very different types of metrics, but anyway, which is how תוספות
Tosafot understands the answer. No, שאני התם דאמר קרא אשר לא עובד
בה, shani hatam de-amar kra asher lo uvad ba, that was not
worked מכל מקום, mi-kol makom, it was not worked in any fashion,
meaning that somehow the פסוק pasuk 'not worked' doesn't just mean you,
it means that even if it was worked even slightly for your
purpose, even if it was also something that was being done for
its purpose, nevertheless work was done to it, that invalidates it. אי
הכי, ei hakhi, says the גמרא, Gemara, אפילו רישא נמי, afilu reisha
nami, if that's true, then even the first part where it just
incidentally threshes the grain, what's the difference? The גמרא Gemara says, no,
הא לא דמיא אלא להא דתנן, ha lo damya ela le-ha de-tnan,
no, that's similar to the following משנה, mishna and this now is
by פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. שכן עליה עוף, shakhan aleha of, if
a bird just happened to rest on the cow, כשרה, kshera, it's
valid. עלה עליה זכר, ala aleha zakhar, if a male went up
on it, right, if it copulated with it, פסולה, psula, it's invalid.
So now either way it's just by itself, you didn't do it
intentionally. So מאי טעמא, mai ta-ama, what's the difference? כדרב פפא, ki-de-Rav
Pappa, דאמר רב פפא, de-amar Rav Pappa, אי כתיב עובד וקרינן עובד,
ei khtiv uvad ve-krinan uvad, if it just said 'had not been
worked', הוה אמינא אפילו ממילא, hava amina afilu mi-meila, I would have
said even if it happened all by itself and was completely regardless
of how you felt about it, and maybe even just a bird
on it is that it's somehow supporting the weight of a bird,
okay. ואי כתיב עבד וקרינן עבד, ve-ei khtiv avad ve-krinan avad, had
it been written 'had you not worked it' and that's how we
read it, הוה אמינא עד דעבד בה איהו, hava amina ad de-avad
ba ihu, you have to directly do something with it.
So even if something happens at your property that
it threshes or that it copulates with this male or whatever, as
long as you didn't physically and directly do it, maybe it would
not invalidate.
השתא דכתיב עבד וקרינן
עובד,
hashta de-khtiv avad
ve-krinan
uvad, it says you don't, the letters are without the vav, so
it could be, it's written to mean you directly, חסר, khaser, you
directly worked it. But it's read passive, it was worked. So בעינן
עובד דומיא דעבד, ba-inan uvad dumya de-avad, what invalidates it is even
if it happens by itself, if it's similar to as if you
had done it directly, which would mean what? מה עבד דניחא ליה,
ma avad de-ni-kha lei, the same way when you had done it
means it's something you wanted, אף עובד דניחא ליה, af uvad de-ni-kha
lei, if it happened by itself but it's something you'd be happy
with. You might remember this is similar to a גמרא Gemara earlier
about if food gets wet, whether it's considered susceptible for טומאה, tuma,
that you don't have to directly get it wet, but you have
to be happy with the fact that it did get wet. Okay,
so here too, you don't have to directly work it, you just
have to be happy with what was done. In general, you would
want your animal to copulate, you would not in general care about
whether a bird rested on an animal. Okay, in the case of
the threshing, it might be like just that it's trivial, you've got
your other animals are threshing anyway, you really don't care so much
whether this animal threshes or not, okay, which is interesting because a
little bit it does benefit you, but it's sort of like, eh,
big deal, okay. But if you intentionally put it in in order
to thresh, even though you also wanted it to nurse, since you
did want it to do work, that is enough to invalidate it,
but that's a special הלכה halakha there, that's not relevant for us
and for the discussion of level of care. Now I do want
to point out that תוספות Tosafot raises the obvious question, which is,
if this is a cow that can be used for a פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, what the heck does it mean that you are
happy that it copulated with this male? Okay, that's going to invalidate
it for being used for a פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, and of
course it's like you'd much rather that that didn't happen, it's much
more valuable as a פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah. So תוספות Tosafot says, well, we must say what it
means is is that had this not been a פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah,
in general this is a type of a thing that you would
want your cows to be doing because they produce baby cows this
way, and therefore we measure it based on that, we don't measure
it based on given the fact that it's a פרה אדומה. Parah
Adumah. Then it would never be considered to be ניחא ליה, ni-kha
lei, right,
except if you actively had worked it yourself. But so we measure
it by what would be the circumstances had it not been a
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. That's what תוספות Tosafot says, which is interesting,
because it raises interesting questions about like, it comes up a similar
thing by שבת Shabbat about a classic definition called like פסיק רישא
דלא ניחא ליה. psik reisha de-lo ni-kha lei. You know, you something
happens incidentally and you're not intending it, but it's definitely going to
happen. And the question is, it's more of a problem if you're
happy with the result than if you don't care about the result.
So a classic case is, you know, you open up the fridge,
you know you forgot to turn off, take out the light bulb,
so you open up the fridge. You're not really intending for the
light bulb to go on, right, but it's definitely going to happen.
So the a key question here is is that are you happy
that it happens or not? So normally you would say, yeah, you're
happy it happens, that's why they put a light bulb in there,
because it makes it more, you're more able to see what's in
the fridge, right? But like, you know, but then some פוסקים, poskim,
because obviously it's a difficult situation, what do you do, you forgot
to take out your light bulb, are you supposed to not open
your fridge on שבת Shabbat or whatever. So some פוסקים poskim say
stuff that to me sounds like a little mind-boggling, like so I've
heard that some people quote like the Rav saying, well, if a
light is on in the room, then it's לא איכפת ליה lo
ikhpat lei because you already, you have the light of the room,
you don't need the light in the fridge, which is not true,
because they wouldn't put a light in the fridge, you know. So
when you're in the fridge, it's harder to see even though you
may have a direct light shining into the fridge, okay, but normally
it's harder to see without the interior light, okay, so then somebody
else says, I think רב Rav Ovadia Yosef says, well, it's לא
ניחא ליה lo nicha leh because you don't like spending the few
pennies on the electricity, you'd rather... which is like again then why
would they have that if that was not something that you would
want? But the most interesting answer, which I think is... I think
they say it in this case is, it's לא ניחא ליה lo
nicha leh because you'd rather the light not go on so it
wouldn't lead to a חילול שבת chilul Shabbos problem. Which is like
okay then everything is לא ניחא ליה lo nicha leh then it's
always מותר mutar to do things you know that happen incidentally because
you would rather it not happen so it wouldn't be a שבת
Shabbos problem. Anyway, that's similar to this, like תוספות Tosafos says, if
you measure it by you know, I'd rather it never do anything
because then it would פסול posul it as a פרה אדומה. parah
adumah. But he says that's not how we measure it here, we
measure whether you would want it or not, you know, under normal
circumstances, not given the reality that it's going to invalidate it as
a פרה אדומה. parah adumah. It's not talking about your borrow, it's
not talking about your borrowing a parah, or you've found someone's parah
adumah, that's a separate... Right, so תוספות Tosafos has that discussion, right,
maybe it has to only be the owner who impacts it, is
that what you mean? Well, just if we're talking... oh yeah, we're
not talking about אבידה aveida at all, which is basically תוספות's Tosafos's
point, like what type of a comparison is it? Which is what
תוספות Tosafos says the answer of the גמרא Gemara is, there's a
פסוק, pasuk, there's a question about did it do work that you
know, did it do work or not do work that you were
happy with? It's not this אבידה aveida question, it's a completely different
question. Okay, so we didn't really answer that. We move on though.
כלי כסף klei kessef וכלי נחושת משתמש בהן silver and and copper
vessels you use it so that it doesn't get rusty. תנו רבנן:
Tanu rabanan: המוצא כלי עץ Hamotzei klei eitz משתמש בהן כדי שלא
ירקבו, mishtamesh bahen kedei shelo yirkavu, you find wooden ones you use
them so it doesn't rot. כלי נחושת Klei nechoshes משתמש בהן בחמין
אבל לא על ידי האור, mishtamesh bahen be-chamin aval lo al yedei
ha-ur, if you have a copper ones, use it in hot water
but not directly by the fire, with hot you know liquids or
whatever hot food but not directly on the fire, like if you
have a copper frying pan, don't use it, don't fry on it
because then it'll obviously it'll it'll wear it out. That's so not
true. The best utensils are directly on the flame are made of
copper. To use... No, but they it helps the vessel to be
used on the flame? It it doesn't hurt the vessel to be
used on the flame. Maybe, maybe. The best chefs in the world
have all copper. I know, but does that mean that it doesn't
wear it out a little bit? Okay, so don't wear it out.
Here you're only doing it to maintain it. It won't wear it
out. It won't blacken it? It'll blacken it. It'll be משחירן. mashchiran.
It's oxidizing it. Yeah, משחירן, mashchiran, it's משחירן, mashchiran, שחור, shachor, yeah,
I guess you're right, yeah, משחירן. mashchiran. Okay. Okay, so anyway it'll
blacken it. Okay, so כלי כסף משתמש בהן בצונן, mishtamesh bahen be-tzonen,
you can use it with cold, אבל לא בחמין, aval lo be-chamin,
not with hot, מפני שמשחירן, mipnei she-mashchiran, it blackens them. מגריפות וקרדומות,
magrefos ve-kardumos, some types of like shovels and like picks, משתמש בהן
ברך, mishtamesh bahen be-rach, you can use it like I know with
soft, like I guess to you know shovel ashes or something, אבל
לא בקשה, aval lo be-kasha, but not like to break up logs
or hard things, מפני שפוחתן, mipnei she-pochasan, that could cause them to
like be damaged. And now of course the funny thing with all
of this as תוספות Tosafos points out is is that why are
we telling me to use it? Why don't we just tell me
to I don't know like to polish it or something? So here
תוספות Tosafos says, well because here actual use does keep it you
know somehow aired out, does keep it in good shape as long
as it's the right type of use, if it's not vigorous use.
But I really don't understand this. To me it would seem the
best thing to do with these things is just to regularly polish
them or something. Silver and copper both tarnish under normal exposure to
air, and to polish them actually removes a small amount of the...
Right, that's true. But what but anyway but is the best way
to maintain these things to use them? I can't understand how use
is good in... Anyway, it's interesting that here they specifically when they
talk about maintenance as opposed to the garment or the ספר תורה
sefer Torah tell you the way you maintain them is by using
them. It's a classic לצורכו ולצורכה, le-tzorko u-le-tzorkah, but תוספות Tosafos feels
that it's just you know ways that will not lead to damage
if you follow these parameters. Okay, כלי זהב וכלי זכוכית, gold and
and glass, לא יגע בהן, don't touch them עד שיבא אליהו. ad
she-yavo Eliyahu. כדרך שאמרו באבידה כך אמרו בפקדון. kederech she-amru ba-aveidah kach
amru be-pikadon. The same way they said by an אבידה aveida they
would say if you were given entrusted an object to watch. פקדון
מאי עבידתיה גביה? pikadon mai avidteih gabeih? If you've been entrusted the
object, what what's it doing? Why are you using it? Because the
point is if you let the owner come and use it. Okay,
if using it is good for keeping it fresh or whatever, so
you know why am I using it? Let the owner come and
use it on a regular basis. אמר רב הונא בר חמא אמר
רב ששת: amar Rav Huna bar Chama amar Rav Sheshes: בפקדון שהלכו
בעליהם למדינת הים, be-pikadon she-halchu ba'aleihem li-medinas ha-yam, because they're not around,
so you're the one that's supposed to be maintaining it, okay. מצא
שק או קופה שאין דרכו ליטול הרי זה לא יטול. matza sak
o kuppah she-ein darko litol harei zeh lo yitol. Now we move
on to the next important point, which is a completely different point,
that if it's not normal to take, let the גמרא Gemara is
going to say, mean it's beneath your dignity, then you don't have
to take it. So מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Where do
you know this from? דתנו רבנן. detanu rabanan. והתעלמת מהם. vehitalamta mehem.
So the verse is written rhetorically, כי תראה את שור אחיך או
את שיו נדחים והתעלמת מהם. ki tireh et shor achicha o et
seiyo nidachim vehitalamta mehem. Would you think that you could ignore it?
No, השב תשיבם לאחיך, hashev teshivem le'achicha, you have to return it.
But here this is being read as non-rhetorical. You may ignore it.
There are circumstances where you may abandon it. פעמים שאתה מתעלם, pe'amim
she'ata mitalem, there are times that you're allowed to hide yourself from
it, to abandon it, ופעמים שאי אתה מתעלם, u-pe'amim she'ei ata mitalem,
and times you cannot. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? What's the difference? היה
כהן והיא בבית הקברות. haya kohen ve-hi be-veit hakvarot. If you were
a כהן kohen and it was in a cemetery, so you'd have
to transgress a prohibition. או שהיה זקן ואינו לפי כבודו, o she-haya
zaken ve-eino lefi kevodo, or you're an older person and it's beneath
your dignity. או שהיתה מלאכתו מרובה משל חברו, o she-hayta melachto meruba
mi-shel chaveiro, or if you would lose out more work than it
would cost you more to return it than the object was worth.
In all of those cases, לכך נאמר והתעלמת מהם. lechach ne'emar vehitalamta
mehem. In those cases you're allowed to abandon it. Okay, למאי איצטריך
קרא? lemai itztrich kra? Now the גמרא Gemara says that's a nice
דרשה, drasha, which one of those three applications were really what we
needed the פסוק pasuk for? אילימא לכהן והיא בבית הקברות, ilima le-kohen
ve-hi be-veit hakvarot, if it's for the כהן kohen and the object
is in a cemetery, פשיטא, peshita, you don't need a פסוק pasuk
for that. האי עשה והאי לא תעשה ועשה. hai asei ve-hai lo
ta'asei ve-asei. There's an עשה asei of returning it, but that's going
up against is the לא תעשה lo ta'asei of a כהן kohen
not becoming טמא tamei and the עשה asei of קדושים תהיו. kedoshim
tihyu. So an עשה asei doesn't push off an עשה asei and
a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. Now רש״י asks that the אבידה avedah
also has a לא תעשה lo ta'asei of לא תוכל להתעלם, lo
tuchal lehitalem, that you can't ignore it, but the לא תעשה lo
ta'asei does not have the force to push off a prohibition, meaning
what would allow me to push away a prohibition is the positive
mandate to do something, the עשה. asei. So if the עשה asei
goes against a negative, then it wins. But if it goes against
a negative and a positive, then they're two, like then it's going
against a negative, it's like something pushing me against an obstruction and
then it conquers the obstruction. But if it's an עשה asei against
an עשה, asei, they're pushing in opposite directions and it doesn't work.
Okay, the לא תעשה lo ta'asei doesn't act as a pushing force.
So the fact that I also have a לא תעשה lo ta'asei
telling me don't ignore it doesn't help me. The pushing force is
the עשה asei and because it's of השב תשיבם, hashev teshivem, it's
going up against don't become טמא tamei and קדושים תהיו kedoshim tihyu
by כהנים kohanim and therefore I know I can't return it. So
I do not need in that case a special פסוק pasuk to
tell me. The normal mechanics of עשה asei and לא תעשה lo
ta'asei tell me don't return it, yes. But what is this saying,
this is only for these specific types of objects, normally a כהן
kohen is supposed to go in a graveyard and get something that's
lost to return. No, no, no, what the ברייתא baraita is saying,
there's the משנה's mishna talking about one scenario, זקן ואינו לפי כבודו.
zaken ve-eino lefi kevodo. The ברייתא baraita is talking about three distinct
scenarios that you don't return it. One scenario has nothing to do
with dignity, has to do with becoming טמא tamei if you're a
כהן. kohen. That's a case you don't return it. Scenario number two,
also nothing to do with dignity, has to do with the loss
of your income as a result of your returning it, too high
of a cost. And scenario three is beneath your dignity. Three completely
independent applications and the גמרא Gemara is now saying that some of
those we could have figured out without the פסוק. pasuk. But this
is all on our משנה mishna which is talking about... Right, but
the only one that matches our משנה mishnah is the זקן ואינו
לפי כבודו. zaken ve-eino lefi kevodo. Okay, but we're bringing in this
דרשה drasha that introduces two other scenarios, okay? Right, but our משנה's
mishnah only the scenario of זקן ואינו לפי כבודו, zaken ve-eino lefi
kevodo, yes. So if the כהן kohen is legitimately in a cemetery,
for instance to bury a... Yeah, that might be different. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara says yes, okay. So anyway, ולא אתי עשה ודחי לא
תעשה ועשה. ve-lo ati asei ve-dachi lo ta'asei ve-asei. The two, לא
דחינן איסורא מקמי ממונא. lo dachinan issura mi-kamei mamona. Number two is
also the prohibition of becoming טמא tamei is a sort of more
of a ritual prohibition and something that's about monetary issues normally doesn't
carry as much weight because that's true about getting money back to
the owner and so on, but that's not the sort of, it's
interesting about like that's somewhat a little bit more fungible because at
the end of the day it's like money in some it's not
as like inviolate as איסור, issur, like the idea of הפקר בית
דין הפקר, hefker beit din hefker, I don't want this to be
misinterpreted like interpersonal obligations are less weighty than like religious obligations. No,
no, but I don't think so as we're going to see in
a minute. For example, for example, the fact that if it costs
me too much to return it I don't have to return it,
that we wouldn't say, 'Wow, if it costs me too much to
keep שבת Shabbat this week I don't have to keep שבת,' Shabbat,
right? It's monetary obligations have more to do with a certain sort
of fungibility, maybe that's not the right word, but anyway of money,
it's like a הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker beit din hefker. These
are things which are more like yes money is lost but money
is always something that can be replaced as opposed to something that's
like a ritual violation, there's no way that that somehow can be
rectified or there's no substitute for that. So anyway, interesting to more
unpack this but that's the way I understand it, not as a
statement of moral... less important, but of like what types of things
can be can there be a substitute for? If you lose that
money, you can always reimburse somebody, you know. It's not as much,
if שבת Shabbos is broken, you broke שבת, Shabbos, you know, it
can't be corrected. What's the context within which it's said מחלל שבת
אחד כדי לשמור שבתות הרבה? mechalel Shabbos echad kedei lishmor Shabbasos harbe?
That's פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Okay. So okay, so that's תרומה terumah
in a cemetery. Are you supposed to go get it? No, no,
no. So okay, so גמרא Gemara says, okay, אלא, ella, so anyway,
even עשה דוחה לא תעשה asei docheh lo sa'asei would not work
in monetary matters, which are seen as somewhat more not as absolute
in certain circles as we're going actually see here. The fact that
you don't have to do a מצות עשה mitzvas asei and a
לא תעשה lo sa'asei because it's not according to your dignity shows
that when it's about protecting money, it's there's
something that's a little less absolute about it, which I know is
a troubling idea, but that be that as it may. Okay, אלא,
ella, fine, maybe what we need the פסוק posuk for is לשלו
ומשלו של חבירו. leshelo umishelo shel chaveiro. If, you know, if you're
going to lose out more money by returning it than the object
is worth. So that, the גמרא Gemara says, מדרב יהודה אמר רב
נפקא, miderav Yehuda amar Rav nafka, we learn this from a different
דרשה. drasha. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
אפס כי לא יהיה בך אביון, effes ki lo yihyeh becha evyon,
except if there is no poor person in you then you don't
have to worry about lending money to the poor. That's the context.
From that we learn שלך קודם לשל כל אדם, shelcha kodem leshel
kol adam, אפס כי לא יהיה בך אביון. effes ki lo yihyeh
becha evyon. The first point is make sure that you're not poor
before you worry about everybody else being poor or not. Okay, it's
a context, a classic variation of right, of like חייך קודמים לחיי
אחיך. chayecha kodmin lechayei achicha. Your first obligation, it's a very important
principle. If you ask what are some of the basic ethical obligations,
principles in Judaism, I one of the most basic ones is, you
know, your taking care of yourself comes before taking care of other
people, right? It doesn't mean like all of my wants come before
everybody else's needs, but like but you know, the base, you know,
my base needs come before other people's base needs. That's חייך קודמים,
chayecha kodmin, and your money comes before other people. Protecting your money
rather than protecting him. Why should I lose out a thousand dollars
to protect your hundred dollars? I have a prior obligation to protect
my thousand dollars. Okay, so that obligation to protect myself from losing
comes before my obligation to protect you from losing. So see when
we're entering into ממונות mamonos issues, we start making certain types of
tradeoff considerations you would not make in the ritual sphere, right? And
that's similar to the issue we made before. So the גמרא Gemara
says both of these things are true. You don't become טמא, tamei,
you don't return it if you're going to lose out more than
the other person would gain, okay. But you don't need the פסוק
posuk of והתעלמת מהם. vehitalamta mehem. So what you need the פסוק
posuk of והתעלמת מהם vehitalamta mehem is for what our משנה teaches,
and we'll end with this for today. אלא, ella, says the גמרא,
Gemara, לזקן ואינו לפי כבודו. lezaken ve'eino lefi kevodo. What you need
the פסוק posuk for is our משנה where it's not a case
of your money versus somebody else's money, but it's your dignity versus
somebody else's money. And that's a principle of כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyos.
So for the principle, that principle of כבוד הבריות, kevod habriyos, that's
what we need that even that can override protecting somebody else's money.
Okay, now, but תוספות Tosafos has an interesting discussion of cases where
כבוד הבריות kevod habriyos even overrides ritual obligations. For example, the fact
that if you find a מת מצוה, meis mitzvah, a body that's
laying there, dead body, that you would bury it even if it
would prevent you from doing a קרבן פסח korban Pesach or bringing,
doing a ברית מילה bris milah for your son or whatever
the case might be. So there's a case where dignity overrides even
ritual, not just monetary obligations. So תוספות Tosafos says oh, but it
has to do with degree of dignity, meaning to have a body,
right, there, you know, just like abandoned in
the middle of the street is a tremendous affront to human dignity
more than me to stoop down and look around for somebody to
return their object even if I'm an important person. Okay, so sometimes
תוספות Tosafos says
the human dignity is so great that it would override, you know,
you know, even ritual obligations, sometimes it's not as great and it
overrides monetary obligations. So we'll continue with this whole discussion tomorrow.